You got to be prepared. And you got to recognize too, that it's not personal. She's not trying to shit on you. She's not trying to be nasty to you.
On the contrary, a girl will only give a shit test to a guy that she is seriously considering.
She won't waste her time with a guy that she does not take seriously. Yeah, I should test when you start getting shit tests from the girl,
it means that you're on track with the girl, okay? And that's why you have to prepare this shit.
Don't think that you can just laugh it off some shit tests these shit tests, they're very, very serious. Because see,
a girl will never really want you until you have passed the shit tests that she puts on you. Okay, so understand how crucial they are.
But don't freak out about it. The way you have to handle them is with humor. What are shit tests? I mean, this is a reasonable question.
And men get hit by shit tests from women all the time. So the question what are shit tests is simply put, they are compliance tests,
they are tests to make sure that the item in question is up to spec. Let me explain z A lot of times a woman will shit test a guy.
Now what does that mean? That's a colloquialism from game shit test, right.
And what it means is that basically a woman will say something to a guy who that will put him like off balance,
she will poke at him to see if he is as manly and assured and confident as he is projecting himself to be. You say, I mean, like, for instance,
with a product testing a compliance test of a product, you you take some products, I don't know your man manufacturing some widget, right?
And you take that product and you you start taking it apart and trying to break it to see if it is up to standard, you know, if it breaks very easily,
then clearly it fails the compliance test and the product is no good. But if it breaks, but it's actually very hard to break it,
it requires X amount of force, I mean, who knows a ton of force or whatever, for the widget to break, then you say, Oh, it's in compliance,
it's within the parameters, right?
That's what a woman is doing with a guy when she should test she is trying to ensure that the confidence that he is projecting is actual and not a lie.
Because you see, it's very easy for a guy to pretend to be something that he isn't, okay. You see a guy like at, you know,
some club and he's dressed really nicely, right? And he's like, very well groomed and maybe has like, I don't know,
like a gold chain or some shit like that. Right? And so what is he projecting he is projecting out in the world out into the world,
projecting to women that he has a good income that he you know, has resources. And you know, the the gold chain and the nice expensive flashy clothes.
They're all to make sure that people know that he has resources right there a signal, okay? He's not flashing around like a wad of bills,
but the clothes are basically acting the same way. Right? And so what will a girl do to to see if he's for real? She'll shit test him. And she'll say,
Oh, well, what are you driving? And if the guy sort of like Wilson says, you know, something like, Oh, well, I came on the bus.
Then she realizes that the facade you know, the expensive clothes, the potential jewelry, which I find just absurd, but whatever.
Or whatever the fuck, that is all a facade. That's what you'll realize. If you came on a bus, it means that you didn't have a pot to piss in, right?
If he came in a limo with his own driver, you know, and his actual driver, not like a hired limo, but like, you know,
a limo driver that works for him. 24 seven, then she'll be like, Oh, you know, he's the real deal. But you see the problem that girl has seen.
She wants to make sure that the guy she meets who is projecting a certain image is actually that thing you see,
because a guy what's the guy looking for in a woman? A hot woman? That's all he cares about. Right? She could be dumb as a brick, right?
And totally poor. I mean, popper poor, right? It does not matter because what does a guy want in a woman? She wants her to be hot.
If she's sexually attractive, she could be an idiot and poor and he won't mind. Yeah, I mean, come on. Yeah, really, you know, now of course,
because because from an evolutionary perspective, we are pushed towards selecting mates who are attractive, who are physically attractive,
because that will mean that if she is physically attractive, and she has long hair and other certain signs of long term health You know,
it will ensure to us that if we have children with her, these children will be healthy. They might be stupid, but they'll be healthy,
at least you see, I'm saying, right. And so that's why we care about how good looking girl is. We care about, you know, skin without blemishes,
you know, because if she has, like Bella wishes, it's probably because she's six, somehow, we care about her having long, long hair,
because if she has long hair, well, it takes at least a couple of years to grow out hair. That's like shoulder length. Right?
And that means that she has had long term health because, again, you know, certain many illnesses, right? damage a woman's hair, and it falls out.
Okay? This is in the past no longer the case today, but you see what's going on? Just by looking at her,
we can tell if she's sexually attractive or not. But that's not the case for women now,
because what women are looking for in a man is social position, social dominance. That's what they're looking for. Okay?
They are not looking for money. That's what stupid men think. And they are not looking for the guy who's the most attractive again,
that's what stupid guys think. No, no, what they want is social position, a man with a high status,
because a man with a high status means that any child she has with him will be protected. That's what she wants. That's what she wants,
because it's been selected by evolution. Okay, this isn't going to change anytime soon, it will never change insofar as human beings are concerned,
women will always be attracted to a man who has high social position. Okay. And so because of that they have to check.
And that's why they should test. Because if that social position is not obvious to everybody,
she will have to make sure that it's true that she will have to make sure that what the guy is projecting to her is real and not bullshit.
Let me give you a simple example. Leonardo DiCaprio is a famous actor. He's won an Oscar. He's been in a bunch of very successful pictures, right?
Okay, so you see him walking down the street, and there's wearing a baseball cap and a ratty old t shirt, right? Any girl who sees him? Right?
What you're going to think is you're going to think that, oh, that guy is dressed really badly. No, she's gonna say, holy shit. That's the DiCaprio.
He doesn't have to prove his social worth. Because he's the DiCaprio. Everybody knows who he is. He's a famous actor. He can go anywhere, you know,
in private jets. And he's got a boatload of money because of his career, right? He doesn't have to prove anything.
He doesn't have to project anything. He doesn't have to show off how rich he is. He doesn't have to wave around his Oscar.
He doesn't have to do anything because everybody knows. Okay. His social position is the fact that he's at the very tippy top of the social hierarchy.
Because he's Leo DiCaprio, because everybody knows who he is, right? So he doesn't have to do shit,
insofar as proving to some girl is worth his social worth. Because he's Leo DiCaprio. And that's why, you know, he can go to you know,
just a black tie event full of supermodels dressed in a ratty t shirt and shorts and flip flops and old baseball cap without having shaved for three days where everybody else is dressed to the nines.
He just shows up, you know, Crick's a finger at the hottest thing there and that hottest thing there,
she'll leave with him on the spot and go fuck his brains out the capital Ville or wherever the fuck instantly because he's the DiCaprio,
he doesn't have to prove anything. But you do instead Why? Okay, most guys, the vast majority of guys, right?
Because we live in the modernist society that we do we because we live in a society where who we are is not obvious because there is no social history among us.
Because we're all floating independently, we are these floating atoms who collide against one another, right? And so a girl comes across you,
she has no idea how successful you are. She has no idea of your position in your business or career. She has no idea.
So she has to test you to make sure that you are who you claim to be, ergo shit tests.
Now the funny thing is that a lot of guys were very successful with a lot of guys who've got a lot going for them, they fail miserably. Okay.
Because you see in the past in the pre modern era, in a society in a mill you right, first of all, it was relatively small, you know,
it would be between maybe 100 people and maybe 500 people and everybody sort of like knew everybody else,
and everybody had connections to one another. So everybody had a fairly decent idea of who was who, right. That was in the past. I'm talking you know,
at least 100 years ago or if not earlier, but all throughout history before that, okay. But now today in our current value,
where we're all floating independent of one another, since there is no social track record,
since a girl who meets you will have no idea who your parents are. Or who your clan is or who your tribe is or in shit like that.
She will have no idea who you are. So she will have to figure out who you are.
And as she figures out who you are by doing these shit tests to see if you are a confident individual to see if you are a man with actual resources,
or you're just bullshitting to see if you are the man, she thinks you are. She's going to inflict shit tests on you. And it's not personal. Okay?
It's not personal. But it has a very clear purpose. And the tragedy is that a lot of guys who've got a lot going for them fail these shit tests.
They don't know how to handle them. Not only have I seen this in other guys, it's sometimes it's happened to me. Oh, yeah. I mean, more than once,
you know, some girl would shit test me and I didn't know how to handle it. Sometimes I was caught off guard sometimes because the girl was very,
very attractive. I was intimidated. I couldn't think of something on spot. Okay. Because I mean, like anybody any guy will tell you of course,
is a lot of times you know, a very attractive girl will, her mere presence will rob you of like, the 15 to 25 IQ points for crying out loud.
It's it's kind of pathetic, but it's the truth. You know?
You come across some girl that's very attractive or whom you consider very attractive a lot of times you get all insecure nervous and you Bumble around like a fucking retard.
But Wow, that's life. That's one of the problems but anyway, it's happened to me. It's happened to every guy.
A girl will give you some shit test and you will fail it you will fail it even though you would have complied even though she was shit testing you to see if you were confident she was shit testing you to see if you were successful shit testing you for whatever fucking reason,
you would have passed the shit test. But you got nervous. Yeah, it happens to every guy. no exception. And so don't worry about it. Yeah,
don't worry about it. But by the same token, you know, don't learn to live with it. Okay. You know, I'm saying I mean, what I'm saying is basically,
you got to learn to deal with shit tests. You got to learn how to handle a woman when she throws a shit test your way.
And how do you learn to do it by fucking practice? Yeah, going out there. Yeah, the more times you are hit with a shit test,
the better you will be at responding to it. Especially the more you understand what is going on, the better you will do with shit tests.
The first step is to classify What the shit test is about a girl will shit test you to see if you have confidence as opposed to Ursa. It's confidence.
She's going to shit test you to see if you have resources, she's going to shit test you to see if you have social connections and more importantly,
if you're socially adroit if you're socially on the ball, okay, and she will shit test you to see if this is the trickiest one of them all. You see,
she will shit test you to see if she is the best thing you've ever been with. Or if you've been with better. Yeah,
let me start with this one guys compete for women. But of course, women compete for guys. Oh, yeah, they compete ruthlessly with one another, okay.
And a woman is always looking for a guy who can attract a girl who is better than her. Okay. This happened to me a bunch of times over the years,
you know, like, I wanted to date girl a. And she was like, say like an eight, right?
And she didn't really want to date me or she wasn't really that interested. But then she spotted me dating a girl who was a nine or a 10.
And automatically. I was fascinating to her. Yeah, yeah, girls always want to be dating a guy who can get the girl who's hotter than her. Okay.
I mean, in the case of guys, because I know this, you know,
a lot of times a guy will be relatively insecure about trying to date a girl who's dated a guy that they believe is a better than they are.
He's going to feel insecure. And you know, it's not going to be an easy thing for the guy, right?
But girls are they get off on trying to land the guy who has been with better women than them hotter women than them.
Women always know who's the hottest girl, okay, they have their their sexual hierarchy very, very clear in their heads, okay.
And so because of this because they are so clear as to you know, this is the hottest girl, this is the second hottest girl, the third, fourth, fifth,
and they know exactly where they are in that hierarchy. When they know that you date a higher status girl than them, they want you more. Okay.
And so a lot of times, they will try to suss out from you. What can Have a woman you usually date? You see? Yeah. And it'll be subtle.
They'll ask you a little cues or what have you, and tried to figure out, you know, well, was he dating like, 10? Or was he dating like an eight?
Because maybe she's like a nine just for the sake of argument, right? And so if you were dating a 10, before, then she'll want to date you.
But if she figures out that you were dating, like an eight or a seven, she's not going to give you the time of day. No way. Of course not.
Because that's how women work. Okay? They want the better guy, the guy who dated the 10. And so if you dated a seven or six, fuck you,
you're not going to get with that girl who's a nine. No way. Because she's not going to be wanting to be with a guy like that. It's as simple as that,
you know, you will have failed the compliance test. You see, of course, if it's clear that you've dated the 10, then you have no problem. Okay?
And what's funny is that see, a lot of times you date the girl who's a 10, okay? And they know for a fact that you dated the 10.
And they're not going to give you any shit test at all. Okay? Because if they know for a fact that you dated this girl who was a 10,
and you dated her, it doesn't matter if it was like a week or a month or a year, but you dated her, you're no longer with her.
The girl who is a nine is going to be thrilled to be dating you and she's not going to give you any shit test. Yeah,
because she's going to know that she is reaching for somebody higher. She's going to know for a fact,
because she will assume that the girl who was a 10 already gave you shit tests. You see, see,
see a girl who knows that you are with somebody else who is better.
She assumes that you already went through all the hoops of a normal shit test because all girls give shit test to guys, all of them.
So if you're like Leo DiCaprio, right, where everybody knows where you are on the totem pole. Leo DiCaprio has probably never had a shit test.
Not as an adult. No way because everybody knows who he is. Right? So no girl in her right mind is going to shit test him. On the contrary,
because he's such a high positions high status guy. Most girls are going to be fucking scared of him. Yeah, very scared of him.
So if you really want to avoid shit tests, that's what you have to do. You have to create some sort of social proof.
That is so obvious that no girl will dare to shit test you. This is of course, assuming that you're not good with shit tests, right?
If you're not good with shit tests, then rather than try to get good at shit tests, you should have something that is so obvious,
so untouchable that no girl in her right mind would dare to question it. And that's why so many guys get flashy cars. Yeah,
because the flashy car like the Bentley or the Lamborghini or wherever the fuck whatever.
vulgar piece of shit that they spent a boatload on automatically means that the guy's got means he's got a lot of money. Okay.
And so a lot of times a lot of guys who are not very good with shit tests, what are they going to do? They're gonna get the expensive car,
the really flashy car, the flashy car that is just like, you know, all bells and whistles, right?
And that screams to everybody that he's got a shit ton of money. Yeah, that way. They avoid shit tests. But here's the thing.
There are multiple shit tests, right? The lesser quality women are interested in the money shit test. Right?
The higher quality women are interested in the brains shit test and the social proof shit test. Yeah. And see, that's why you know,
you see a lot of these guys who are rich but stupid. they wind up with these over made up over dressed up. Women with the big boobs or the boobs.
They're just shoved in your face guy who are just like pathetic, right? I mean, those kinds of girls like trashy girls, right?
Those guys who drive the Lamborghini wind up with the trashy girls. Yeah. Because the higher quality girls, right, the more decent girls.
The brain year smarter girls. Yeah. They see a guy with the flashy car and they don't buy his brand bullshit. Yeah, because they know.
They know that all he's got is money. But that's it. Same with the brainy stuff. See, guy who's really brainy. Presumably you for instance,
you're really fucking brainy. And you show off how fucking smart you are. This works with the brain girls who don't give a shit about anything else.
Right? The the nerdy girls the girls with glasses, right? They care about a really smart guy. But they are not necessarily the hottest girl. You see,
there are different kinds of girls will pay attention to different shit tests. And the other girls will ignore that guy. See? The really hot,
dressed up girl, you know the model, for instance? She's not going to pay attention to the brainy guy. Okay, because she's gonna say correctly,
that the brainy guy all he's got is brains, but he doesn't have money and he doesn't have social position. Fuck them. Yeah, yeah, that's how it works,
what you want to be as an all rounder, you want to be an all rounder in the sense of, you know, being able to show a little bit of money,
a little bit of brains a little bit of social position. And the fact that you've dated somebody of a woman of a higher status than the girl,
you're after you want all four. Because if you focus on just one, you're going to get, essentially a distorted woman,
a woman who prioritizes just one thing over the others. You see what I'm saying? Just like the guy who shows off the flashy car,
and he's going to attract the bimbo. Right? who only cares about money, the gold digger who only cares about money. Yeah,
and just as the brainy guy who shows off how smart he is, he's gonna attract the nerdy girl who is not particularly attractive, you know? The same,
you see what I'm saying here, you're gonna attract a very narrow kind of girl, if you're only good with one kind of shit test.
That's why you have to be good at all the shit tests, you know, see, I'm saying, once again,
I'm sort of like not explaining what the fuck I'm trying to say. And I have notes and everything, you know,
I, I try to think of this shit and prepare for the shin. You know, I start talking, I sound like a fucking retard, or the ideas I wrote down seemed,
you know, better than they actually were word of the photo, you know, I'm just complaining. But anyway, the point I'm trying to make here is that see,
you got to be an all around. And the only way to get good at chatez is to go out there, interact with a lot of women,
and figure out what their priorities are. Okay? If that's the key ish, you figure out what their priority is,
and they're going to test you on that thing. The gold digger is going to shit test you on how much money you have.
The Brainiac girl is gonna you know should test you on how smart you are, how many books you've read shit like that. You know,
the the social butterfly girl, she's gonna shit test you, in so far as you know, the social position and what parties you go to and shit like that.
Right? And, and the girl who's competing with the other girls,
she's going to shoot test you and try to figure out what quality of woman you are seeing is, each of them has a priority.
And that's when you got to pay attention to what's the priority of the girl. That priority is the thing that she's going to test you on.
And she's going to shit test you multiple times until she gets undeniable proof that you have that thing, okay. I mean, like,
put into simple terms like, you know, insofar as a brainy girl, right? She wants to make sure that you're smart.
And she'll have like brain teasers or ask you about obscure authors or shit like that, right? Something that you know,
a dumbbell with a lot of money who's driving a Lamborghini, you know, he's gonna blow her off. He's not gonna know what the fuck she's talking about.
You know it, she'll mention, you know, Richard Fineman or son, I, then he'll be like, Huh, you know, and instantly,
he fucked up the shit test that she gave him. But you know, she'll do that relentlessly. Until she's absolutely sure. That's how it works.
These shit tests, they don't go away. And they're constant. And you got to be prepared. You got to be prepared. And you got to recognize too,
that it's not personal. She's not trying to shit on you. She's not trying to be nasty to you. On the contrary,
a girl will only give a shit test to a guy that she is seriously considering. She won't waste her time with the guy that she does not take seriously.
Yeah, I should test when you start getting shit tests from the girl. It means that you're on track with the girl. Okay?
And that's why you have to prepare this shit. Don't think that you can just laugh it off some shit tests these shit tests. They're very, very serious.
Because see, a girl will never really want you until you have passed the shit tests that she puts on you. Okay, so understand how crucial they are.
But don't freak out about it. The way you have to handle them is with humor. Yeah, humor always wins and shit tests. Absolutely.
You make a joke about the shit test. If because if you're really confident in whatever it is the quality that she's testing you for.
If you're really confident that quality and you laugh it off laugh offer shit test or do the the the the meta thing of like,
sort of like taking a step back and saying outright Oh, you're shit testing me on this thing? Okay, let's try it. Let's go, you know,
and making a joke about it. That will earn you even more points. Because if you For instance, if you are talking with a brainy girl,
and she starts asking you about Albert Einstein and Richard Fineman and quantum mechanics or some shit like that, and you openly say Oh,
so you want to shit test To me and figure out if I'm a dumbbell or not okay, I can play this game.
Let's talk about Richard Fineman or whatever the fuck, right? If you play it like that, instantly she will know that you passed it.
Basically you do that move and you pass the shit test. Okay? Did it with the money thing, okay? girl says to us Oh, so what car do you drive us to?
Oh, you want to? You want to see if I'm up to stuff that I'll drive you inside. Okay, I can play that game. But of course, the thing is here,
when you do that with the money situation, for instance, you better be driving a fucking good car. Yeah. And ditto with the, the social proof.
The one where we're, uh, you're in a good social company. See,
you better know the people that she knows or know the people that she knows or know that people that she wants to know. Okay? I mean, you see, it's,
it's a dangerous game. You can only do it. You can only pull off this shit. When you're really sure of yourself and you really have the goods.
Because if you don't have the goods,
you're going to look like a fool.