Ladies and gentlemen, permit me, please, to claim your attention for a moment.
In the words of Winston Churchill, in the Second World War
every bond between man and man was to perish.
Crimes were committed
by the Germans under the Hitlerite domination to which they allowed themselves to be subjected
which find no equal in scale and wickedness with any that have darkened the human record.
The wholesale massacre by systematize processes of six or seven millions of men
women and children in the German execution camps
exceeds in horror the rough and ready butcheries of Ganga is calm
and his scale reduces them to pick me proportions.
Deliberate extermination of whole populations was contemplated
and pursued by both Germany and Russia in the eastern war.
The hideous process of bombarding open cities from there
once started by the Germans was repaid 20 fold by the ever mounting power of the allies
and found its culmination in the use of the atomic bombs which obliterated Hiroshima
and Nagasaki.
This video is sponsored by Skillshare
the first 500 people to use the link in the description will get their first two months for free.
Skillshare is an online learning community that you can use to expand your horizons.
With 1000s of classes in design, business, technology and more.
Skillshare has something for everyone
from how to take the best photographs at night to tips on presenting.
You will get classes from experts in their fields
ensuring you have high quality teaching for the subjects you enjoy.
With an annual subscription of less than $10 a month.
Premium membership gives you unlimited access to these high quality classes
so you can improve your skills, unlock new opportunities and do the work you love.
And since Skillshare is sponsoring this video
the first 500 life guide viewers to use the link in the description
will get their first two months for free.
Click on the link in the description and start learning today.
It was a simple a noble policy to keep Germany disarmed after the struggle of the First World War
and the victors sufficiently armed and vigilance.
Pateros was soon made America's failure to enter the League of Nations
the weakness and lack of resolution of Western democracies
to confront the growing strength of the fascist dictators in Germany, Italy and Japan
and the economic turmoil that allowed these events to spark and build.
Upon reflection.
It is all too easy to see and understand how this tragedy could have been avoided.
But for those in power at the time
they failed all too well to see the Gathering Storm that confronted them.
The origins of the Second World War can be found within the confines of the Palace of Versailles.
Germany surrender in the First World War was a shock to both the international community
as well as to its people.
Militarily, Germany had been successful on the Eastern Front.
Troops were deep within France and Germany itself was untouched.
However, on November 11 1918, at 11am, the 11th hour of the 11th day of the 11th month
a ceasefire came into effect
an armistice had been signed and the war to end all wars had come to an end
the proud peoples of Germany had been defeated.
The Allies victorious after four years of suffering and untold casualties
wanted to see Germany pay to ensure something like this would never happen again.
An international institution was to be established
in the hope of bringing about a new world of collective security
latest seen in the form of the League of Nations.
In early 1919.
The Germans were summoned to Versailles
not to negotiate but rather to hear the terms they would have to implement and endure.
David Lloyd George of Great Britain, Woodrow Wilson of America, George Clemens
who of France and Orlando of Italy all attended with the aim of weakening Germany
World War One had radically altered the political European map
with the defeat of the Central Powers including Austria Hungary, Germany
Bulgaria and the Ottoman Empire.
The German state that came out of the Great War
was also to experience profound change and suffer severe territorial losses.
Germany was to lose a portion of its eastern land, creating
a new Polish state and establishing a Polish corridor between Germany and East Prussia
giving Poland access to the sea.
The port city of Danzig, the largest city on the coast was given to the League of Nations
Mabel in the Baltic was handed over to Lithuania, alsace-lorraine to France and
the mineral riches Ireland was to be administered by the League of Nations for a span of 15 years
with the Rhineland, becoming a demilitarized zone, providing France with additional security.
The German colonies in Africa were distributed to the British and the French
and their South Pacific colonies would be given to Japan.
In addition, military clauses were added to the treaty.
The German army could be no larger Than 100,000 troops, they were allowed no air force
no tanks or heavy artillery
and the German Navy could have no more than six warships with no u boats or submarines.
Insults being added to injury, a war guilt clause was placed in the treaty
making Germany accept full responsibility for the outbreak of the war
as it was only on this basis that the Allies could demand reparations.
France and Britain had begun the war as creditor states
but had ended as debtor nations and wanted to be repaid.
The sums being
asked of Germany and reparations were many times more than was possible for them to pay
place in a severe burden on their economy
which later contributed greatly to economic instability and hyperinflation.
JOHN Maynard Keynes, the primary representative of the British Treasury at the time said
I believe that the campaign for security and out of Germany the general costs of the war
was one of the most serious
acts of political and wisdom for which our statesmen have ever been responsible.
The German people believe that had been bitterly betrayed by their high command
and unjustly treated by the international system
views that would lead to materialize throughout the 1920s and 30s.
After the Wall Street Crash of 1929 and the preceding Great Depression
the world was plunged into economic turmoil and Germany was hit hard.
American banks withdrew the loans they had made to Germany and the economy collapsed overnight
due to such large reductions in cash and capital
bank struggle to provide money and credit and so in 1931
there were runs on German and Austrian banks, with several of them closing
businesses closed at an alarming rate and by 1933, unemployment had reached 6 million.
Many people were left homeless and 1000s of children died from malnutrition
a lack of government resolve
and out of despair many turn to alternative political leaders and parties
in the hope that problems would be solved.
One man in particular garnered a lot of attention from his rousing speeches.
And this man was Adolphe Hitler.
Hitler's speeches delivered clear culprits for Germany's problems.
The November criminals who had signed the armistice end in World War One
the liberals and socialists who had signed the Treaty of Versailles
the communists who threatened revolution in Germany
and finally the Jewish bankers who plotted to undermine and destroy the German state.
The Nazi and communist parties both clashed violently
and Hitler claimed to be the only one to bring about order and end the red plague.
As a powerful and gifted public speaker, Hitler was able to capitalize on public discontent.
His party, the National Socialist German Workers Party, or the Nazi Party grew to record levels.
In September of 1930, the Nazi Party had increased its representation in the Reichstag
the German parliament almost tenfold, winning 107 seats, and only two years later, in 1932
they won 230 seats becoming the majority in parliament.
Hitler had found the faders and misery of the Great Depression to his advantage.
Stay tuned for harsh reality has opened the eyes of millions of Germans and the 1932 election
Hitler also run for president, and although he lost a decorated war hero Paul von Hindenburg
his rise in popularity gave president Hindenburg no choice
but to appoint Hitler on the 13th of January 1933.
As Chancellor of Germany, head of the German government
just one month after Hitler had been sworn in as Chancellor
a fire was started in the righteous dag
by a young Dutch communist who was then used to paint all communists as the enemy of Germany.
Using article 48 of the Constitution.
The Reichstag fire decree was passed
that abolished civil liberties such as freedom of speech and freedom of the press.
Shortly after Hitler created a secret police known as the Gestapo
helping him to suppress any and all opposition.
As Chancellor.
He also tripled the size of the German military, violating the Treaty of Versailles, banned
all rival parties killed political opponents
and prohibited Jews from working voting and occupying public spaces.
After the death of President von Hindenburg in 1934, Hitler declared himself fear of Germany
absolute dictator.
Hitler believed the World to Come would be dominated by four main superpowers.
Germany was to be the main hegemonic power of mainland Europe
the British maintaining the international Empire.
The Japanese or the Aaron's of the East has hit the light to call them
would be the main power in Southeast Asia and the Pacific
and finally America would dominate the Western Hemisphere.
Part of Nazi support was their opposition to the Treaty of Versailles.
And upon coming to power Hitler promise to return Germany to its rightful place in the world.
Hitler's objectives were clear
that our economy needed to be self sufficient on what the Germans called economic autarky.
Being able to produce their own goods and not relying too heavily on imports.
This was critical to withstand the British blockade to trade
a policy that had damaged Germany in the First World War.
Germany would also need Lebensraum
or living space that would facilitate the growing German population.
Lebensraum was to be found in the east, and this meant Germany would have to expand into Poland
Czechoslovakia, Ukraine, and agricultural regions of the Soviet Union.
For Hitler, this new German Reich that was to be created was to be racially pure
containing only the area and race
free of Slavs and Jews of whom would have to leave or be eliminated.
And it was also Germany's mission to launch a crusade against Judeo Bolshevism
an ideology and enemy that's home took the form of the Soviet Union
a war he thought would inevitably have to happen.
The international system that had been envisaged was not able to cope.
Without the support of the British
and the United States absence following a policy of non interventionism
France was left alone to maintain and enforce the Treaty of Versailles
something it couldn't and didn't want to do alone.
Held in Geneva, Switzerland
the disarmament conference provided a preview of how Hitler operated
and what future Nazi policy would look like.
Hitler instructed his representatives at the conference
to state that Germany would completely disarm if and only if France, Britain
Japan and the United States would do the same.
This was an offer that Hitler correctly assumed would be denied.
And so he went back to the German people
and showed them how this conference was not about disarmament
but rather keeping Germany subjugated.
And so in 1933, Hitler withdrew from the League of Nations and the disarmament conference
to the support of his people.
In 1934, to the surprise of the international community
Germany signed a non aggression pact with Poland
taken an ally away from France and weakened in France his military positioning
as Germany was now free to the east.
In March of 1935, Germany revealed it had been building an air force the Luftwaffe
again breaking the Treaty of Versailles, with the justification being that Britain
France and Poland all had an Air Force and that Germany too needed to defend itself.
One week later, Hitler declared his intentions to introduce conscription
to build an army of half a million men.
Once again the League of Nations protested, but no action was taken.
The disarmament clauses outlined in the Treaty of Versailles had been destroyed.
Then, in June of 1935, to France's horror, Britain had entered into a naval agreement with Germany.
The Anglo German naval agreement
in which Britain recognized Germany's right to build up its Navy.
They were to be allowed up to 35% of Britain surface tonnage
and a submarine fleet up to 60% that of Britain's
Britain had struck a deal and in doing so had given up on Versailles
given up on Disarmament and began to show Hitler that a policy of appeasement was to be pursued.
A year later, in March 1936, German troops were sent into the demilitarized Rhineland
the matter was referred to the League of Nations, which once again did nothing
remilitarization of the Rhine
was the final nail in the coffin for the Treaty of Versailles and the international order.
The treaty was now officially dead.
France in response to German occupation of the Rhine
constructed imagino line along its eastern border.
However
the fortification stopped at the Arden forest and did not extend across the Belgium frontier
the place at which Germany had entered during the Great War.
The French were preparing for a war of the trenches and were
not prepared for the motorized divisions that made German blitzkrieg tactics so effective.
Stalin at this time threatened by German power and aggression
entered the Soviet Union into the League of Nations
and also signed an agreement with Czechoslovakia, stating he would come to that aid if attacked
but only if the Western Allies would come to its defense burst.
This was to stop the West trying to push German aggression eastwards.
Hitler wanted all German speaking nations in Europe to be unified
especially his native homeland Austria.
Under the terms of the Treaty of Versailles, Germany and Austria were forbidden to be unified
as the Allies hadn't fought for years to see a large Germany, Austrian President schuschnigg
knowing he would receive no help from Italy
and that France and Britain would not interfere in Hitler's plans resigned, and two days later
German troops marched into Austria unopposed, Hitler had successfully annexed Austria
under the guise of national self determination as justification.
After the successful preoccupation of the Rhineland and the annexation of Austria
Hitler turned to Czechoslovakia
of which 3 million people in this date and land were of German origin.
The Czech government
hope that Britain and France would come to its assistance in the event of a German invasion
but British Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain was intent on avoiding war
he made two trips to Germany.
In September and offered Hitler favorable agreements
but the fear kept increasing his demands.
On the 30th of September 1938, Hitler attended a meeting in Munich, accompanied by Britain
France and Italy, all of whom agreed that Hitler should have the Sudetenland
as long as he promised to go no further.
The Soviets in the checks were not represented at the meeting
and realizing that no country would come to their
aid Czechoslovakia were forced to surrender the Sudetenland to Germany.
After the meeting
Chamberlain went to him and asked him to sign a peace treaty between Great Britain and Germany
to which Hitler happily agreed.
Upon his return to Britain
Chamberlain delivered his peace in our time speech to cheering crowds.
To people at the time Neville Chamberlain was a great champion.
The Munich Agreement had won the peace and war was averted.
But from this Hitler saw Europe is weak and unwilling to stand up to his demands.
Winston Churchill, one of Chamberlain's greatest critics said
you were given the choice between war and dishonor, you chose to honor a new half war.
Churchill was proven right when just half a year later on the 15th of March 1939
German troops marched into Chekhov's baqia.
Once again, Hitler had broken an agreement for France in Britain then guaranteed Poland safety
with
Britain also beginning to rearm and install a highly secret radar system along its east coast.
On August 23 1939, the Germans and the Soviet signed a non aggression pact
which sent shockwaves across the world's diplomatic community.
The signing of this pact for Hitler ended the prospect of a two front war
which allowed for a greater taking of Poland.
But for starlin this bought him time to rebuild the Red Army that he had purged.
As the Last Days of Summer arrived, there was a sense in Europe that war was imminent
and the sense was right.
Blitzkrieg or lightning war revolutionized warfare
and allowed an attacker to destroy an opponent before they were even mobilized.
Through the use of tanks or Panzers
German forces were able to quickly smash border defenses and circle enemy troops.
They were to be supported by tactical airpower
the Luftwaffe that provided close aerial support to ground operations.
Using this tactic, Germany was able to quickly knock out opponents
allowing them to conduct operations without the total mobilization of the economy and society
much like the First World War had required.
The First World War was one of attrition
something Germany wasn't in the current position to win or endure.
This new mode of warfare therefore, was to be one of speed and efficiency.
On September 1 1939, Germany with 52 divisions, and over 1 million men made their way into Poland
attacking through the north in the south, destroying the Polish armed forces.
Britain responded with an ultimatum to Germany to cease military operations.
The ultimatum was ignored, and so France, Britain
Australia and New Zealand all declared war on Germany
with Neville Chamberlain broadcasting the announcement on radio.
The German attack was led by five armored divisions containing 300 tanks apiece
followed by four motorized infantry divisions carrying their artillery and equipment
with cover provided from the air by the Luftwaffe.
Believing that the invasion would be stopped by British and French intervention
the Polish was slow to mobilize and poorly prepared to face the German onslaught.
Upon mobilization, the poll sported 1.3 million men
however, possessed outdated equipment and only a few tanks
with the German armored and motorized divisions out number in the Polish 15 to one.
Equipment were so scarce and outdated for the polish
that cavalry squadrons were seen to be charging heavily armored German tank divisions.
The invasion had worked with greater speed and efficiency than planned
and by September 8 Warsaw, the Polish capital had been reached.
Once Germany had broken Polish resistance, Stalin move troops into Poland
being keen to regained territory that had once belonged to Russia before the 1917 revolution.
Poland was now to fight a war on two fronts, something they get couldn't win
and so on the 27th of September 1939, Polish command has negotiated a ceasefire
with the last Polish military unit surrendering on October 6.
Altogether, Poland lost 70,000 troops against the German invaders
and another 50,000 against the USSR with 133,000 been wounded.
The Germans took over 700,000 Polish prisoners
and the Soviets another 300,000 150,000 poles managed to escape
many coming to Great Britain and enlisting in the armed forces.
For Hitler, the invasion of Poland was his third successful annexation of a foreign country.
He had got what he wanted, and the Western powers had once again nothing.
This period became known as the phoney war because Britain and France took no military action.
Despite declaring war on Germany.
Blitzkrieg had been a major success and over the course of The next few months
Hitler continuously said that he didn't want to war in the West.
Three months after the invasion of Poland
Stalin was afraid that Finland would fall under German influence
as Leningrad was only 20 miles away from the finish border.
The Soviets demanded the Finns succeed territory on the karelian estimates
as to put Leningrad out of danger.
The Finns refused, and so the Soviet Union launched military action on the 30th of November 1939.
The Soviet Army outnumbered the Finns 50 to one and equipment out match them in almost every way.
But the Finns fought with great tenacity
were in white uniforms as to blend into the snow and outmaneuver in the Red Army.
Finland resisted Soviet attacks for more than two months and inflicted considerable damage.
After the Soviet military reorganized itself and adopted different tactics
they continued their offensive in February overcoming finished defenses.
The war came to an end in March 1940, with the signing of the Moscow peace treaty
with Finland surrendering 11% of its territory to the Soviet Union.
The dreadful performance of the Red Army and Finland
encouraged Hitler to think that an attack on the Soviet Union would be successful, and
confirmed to the Western powers that the Soviet military was not the best equipped or organized
something that wouldn't be fully tested for another 15 months
with the German launch of Operation Barbarossa.
In April of 1940, Adolf Hitler made a huge strategic gamble.
His plan was to send the whole strength of the German Navy along the Norwegian coast
from Oslo to Novick to protect the coastal waterways.
Swedish iron ore could then be safely transported to German blast furnaces
and German control of Norwegian waters would make an allied blockade of Germany a lot harder.
British discontent over the Norwegian campaign
and an allied withdrawal led to the resignation of Neville Chamberlain on the 10th of may 1940.
His successor was appointed the same day
a man who throughout the 1930s had spoken out regarding German rearmament
and Hitler's threat to the world.
A man who went by the name of Winston Churchill on the 10th of may 1940
Germany launches an attack against France, Belgium, Luxembourg and the Netherlands.
French troops quickly positioned themselves along the Maginot Line, and the
rest of the Allied soldiers positioned themselves along the Belgium and Luxembourg borders.
As Belgium is neutral
Allied soldiers could not enter the country and prepare a defensive position
and so we'd have to wait for Germany to invade.
Germany began their offensive in the early hours of the morning with more than 1000 fighters
bombers and dive bombers.
They attacked
allied airfields destroying the Air Force on the ground before they could even take flight
something that would be crucial in giving the Luftwaffe an
air superiority for the rest of the offensive.
Just three hours after being attacked Belgium permits Allied troops to enter the country
due to the great mobility of German Panzers and motorized infantry divisions
that allied forces never had the time to establish a practical defense
and within the day luxembourgers captured sporty nearly two and a half million men
the German invasion worked with greater efficiency.
Three army groups were to be used for the invasion, Army Group A, B and C.
Army Group B was tasked with defeating the Netherlands
and then advancing into Belgium to keep the Allied forces in place.
Army Group C were to attack through the Maginot Line keeping those soldiers in place
and protecting the flank of Army Group A
comprising of 750,000 troops Army Group A was by far the largest.
They were to push through the Arden forest and naturally fortified area
something the French were not expecting to be entered or breached.
41,000 vehicles successfully made their way through the southern forest.
The Germans then crossed the Meuse river and by May 15 capture sedan.
They then head west katene
often surrounding the entire allied army that had advanced into Belgium.
This unexpected push through the odd den would force Allied soldiers out of Belgium
with them having to withdraw to the port of Dunkirk to protect their flank.
With the Allies completely surrounded by German forces, Winston Churchill
launches are planned to evacuate the British Expeditionary Force from Northern France.
400,000 Allied troops are stranded on the beaches of Dunkirk, and on May 26
Operation Dynamo begins by air
the Luftwaffe are constantly attack the soldier stranded on the beaches and sink many ships
and by land German artillery fires upon the shore.
The Royal Air Force in response launches a counter attack to protect the ships and soldiers.
The beaches at Dunkirk are shallow and even at a high tide.
Destroyers can approach within a mile of the shore
and so the troops would have to be ferried out in small craft.
On the 31st of may hundreds of civilian vessels
known as Little ships make their way across the English Channel to evacuate the soldiers
fishing boats, lifeboats, sailing barges
ferries and supply ships will do their part in bringing the soldiers home.
The British Expeditionary Force had survived
but almost all of the heavy artillery in equipment was left behind.
By the fourth of June 1940 338,000 troops had been evacuated, making the events at Dunkirk
a miracle and the largest evacuation in military history.
The surrender of France followed some Three weeks later
after Mussolini declared war on France and German troops marched into Paris
ceilin France his fate.
In just six weeks from the 10th of may 1940, German forces conquered France, Belgium
Luxembourg and the Netherlands.
By the end of June
Hitler dominated the European continent with victory on a scale never seen before.
What Germany hadn't accomplished in four years in the Great War
had taken Hitler just 35 days which is later become known
as one of the most remarkable military campaigns in history.
The future of the free world hung in the balance.
Britain faced a perilous situation after the fall of France
and all that separated the Germans from yet another victory was the English Channel.
The isolationist United States was an ocean away
which left only one man to make a decision that would change the course of human history.
With the fighting over
Germany began to consider ways of resolving the question of how to deal with Britain.
It's our hope that Churchill would come to his senses and sign a peace treaty.
But if the British refused, Hitler's only option was to invade.
Churchill then delivered his We will fight on the beaches speech.
This famous speech transformed Churchill into a world statesman
outlining unequivocally he would never make peace with Hitler.
But war was now to come.
Germany had to plan an invasion of Great Britain
the invasion of France and Poland had taken months to plan
with every intricate detail of battle thought through
but the invasion of Britain with orders from high command would have to be ready by August 15.
Giving them just one month the British began to dig in.
Coastal defences were constructed across southern England
signposts were removed and replaced to confuse invaders.
Fields were laced with barbed wire to deter airborne troops
and a Home Guard was established full of those who are illegible or too old to fight.
Meanwhile, Hitler began his plan for the invasion of the British Isles
codenamed Operation sea line.
20 divisions were to be deployed in Britain south coast to the use of amphibious landing craft.
However, the English Channel wasn't easy to cross
the Royal Navy was still the largest in the world and despite Empire commitments
Britain's home fleet of ships still far out numbered the German Navy.
The German naval chief Admiral Eric Rader
didn't believe he could seize the English Channel for long enough to get the German army across
for a successful invasion of Britain.
Therefore, Germany would first have to gain control of the sky.
The Luftwaffe are far outnumbered the Royal Air Force in June of 1940
the British had less than 700 operational fighters against 2600 German fighters and bombers.
The odds were daunting.
Both sides sported some of the most advanced planes of the time
the British with their supermarine Spitfire and the Hawker Hurricane
which shot down the most German planes.
These were up against the German Messerschmitt Bf 109.
And these were to be used to escorts German bombers
for use of radar was crucial to the British during the Battle of Britain
and was the world's first integrated air defense system.
Placed along the south and east coast of Britain.
These tool masks could pick up aircraft at a range of 120 miles, given their distance, direction
height and numbers.
This information would then be sent to our air Fighter Command
run by Air Chief Marshal whew doubt in and the closest RF airfields would then be alerted.
On the 10th of July 1940
the Luftwaffe were began to attack ship in traveling across the English Channel
but this was not their main aim.
General Garin
head of the German Air Force focused the German assault on destroying the RF in the sky
there airfields and aircraft production factories.
When the initial assault was launched, airfields were heavily bombed
but none had been put out of action.
British radar gave them plenty of warning and
were able to shoot down the enemy planes in nominal scene dogfights that would consume the sky.
The Luftwaffe had lost 46 aircraft to just 12 British.
Two days later, Goering launched the largest Attack of the whole battle on August 15.
Waves of German bombers destroyed British airfields.
42 British fighters had been destroyed at the cost of 90 German aircraft.
Over the next 12 days guerin's plan continued, and fighters on both sides were suffering.
The Royal Air Force were exhausted
and the German fighters were demoralized as the British seem to always be waiting for them.
But British losses soon began to rapidly increase.
Many men died and planes in airfields were being destroyed at an alarming rate.
If the battle continued along these lines, a German victory would be imminent.
Goering realizing this began to attack at night as well.
However, a major mistake was about to occur.
On the cloudy night of August 24, a group of German bombers lost their way
and accidentally bombed the City of London.
The following night 81 British bombers made their way to Berlin in retaliation
an act that showed Britain could attack as well as defend.
Hitler was furious and began a campaign of bombing London.
On the seventh of September
German bombers attacked London's East End 450 people died and 1000s of homes were destroyed.
But this was a crucial mistake by focusing on London rather than the airfields
RF bases were relieved of pressure and had the time to repair and rebuild aircraft.
One week later, on the 15th of September on what became known as the Battle of Britain day
the Luftwaffe embarked on an all out attack against London, which they
believe would break fighter commands resistance and pave the way for a successful invasion.
The ra f successfully fought the incoming wave of lift warfare formations
destroying 61 aircraft the highest losses the Luftwaffe had suffered for over a month
with the RF only losing 31 aircraft.
The 15th of September can be seen as an overwhelming and decisive defeat for the Luftwaffe.
They had failed to gain air superiority over Great Britain and on September 17
just two days later, Hitler postponed operation sea lion.
With the help of foreign pilots, especially those of Poland, France and Czechoslovakia
the Royal Air Force were able to repel a Nazi invasion.
To show his appreciation to all those who fought Churchill said the following.
Never in the field of human country was so much owed by so many can cope.
With the invasion of Britain no longer possible.
Hitler turned his attention eastwards
Germany was now to focus on the largest military operation in human history
Operation Barbarossa the invasion of the Soviet Union.
The fighting was not over.
However, the Blitz had now begun.
British cities were bombed and night raids
and London was attacked every night for 57 consecutive nights by one and on November 10 1940
a 14th Century Gothic cathedral in Coventry was obliterated.
Children were evacuated to the countryside
and people living in London spent most nights sleeping in air raid shelters
are in the London Underground.
A blackout was enforced after darkness where all sources of light
had to be covered up as to prevent the Germans from seeing where towns and homes were located.
Over the course of the Blitz, which lasted eight months and five days
just under 2 million homes were destroyed
and 40,000 civilians were killed with 87,000 been seriously injured.
But most importantly, the bombing had failed to demoralize the British into surrender.
The full force of the German war machine was now to be turned against the Soviet Union.
This war was to be won to the death, a clash of two ideologies
two forces of civilization in which only one could be victorious.
Hitler hated communism, and victory over the Soviet Union
would provide Germany with the abundant natural resources
that would enable the German people to finally become the master race.
Operation Barbarossa was Hitler's greatest gamble.
Unable to defeat Great Britain in the West, Germany's armies were deployed to the east.
Luckily for Hitler, the Red Army, the largest in the world had been
devastated by Stalin's purges during the 1930s 10s of 1000s of officers were shot or imprisoned
an inefficiency and a lack of coordination became widespread.
Before the invasion began and to secure Germany's southern flank on April 6 1941
Germany invaded the Balkans.
33 divisions entered Yugoslavia and six days later they surrendered.
Greece then fell and Athens was captured within three weeks
Operation Barbarossa could now commence.
Over 4 million men were to be deployed accompanied by over 3000 aircraft.
Three divisions were also to be used much like the invasion of France.
Army Group North would push through the Baltic states and C's Leningrad
Army Group Center was too advanced to Moscow and Army Group South would occupy the Ukraine
The Red Army was far larger
they had 2 million men along the western front and millions more in reserve.
They also sported 20,000 tanks against Germany 6000 although they were older and less advanced
Germany versus the Soviet Union
would therefore be a war between superior technology and speed versus sheer numbers.
On June 22 1941, the operation began at 3:15am.
The Luftwaffe attacked Soviet airfields while the ground invasion commenced.
Hitler's Panzers then pushed forward and within two days had penetrated more than 50 miles.
The Red Army was no match and 10s of 1000s of Soviet prisoners were rounded up.
As July came blitzkrieg was successful as ever.
Within a week, the Panzers were at Smolensk only a few 100 miles away from Moscow.
It was here that the tanks would rest
so the rest of the army that often relied on horse drawn carriages could catch up.
Prisoners that had been captured along the way, also began heading west to captivity
in which two and a half million men would never return.
Meanwhile, the German advanced in the south was having troubles
and so Hitler ordered Army Group north to swing south to Kiev to provide help
to which his generals heavily objected.
It would turn out to be a disastrous decision.
Soviet manpower seem to be endless
and the whole turret Smolensk allowed Starling to mobilize more than 16 million troops
and a new Soviet tank was headed towards the frontline.
The T 34
which was faster than the Panzer mark for the remnants of Army Group North surrounded Leningrad
modern day St Petersburg.
But rather than capturing the city, the Germans decided to starve it.
Starvation began and more than 11,000 people died in November
and another 3700 on one day in December alone.
The Siege lasted for more than two years, and by the end in 1944
over a million Soviets had been killed.
Army Group Center now prepared for an offensive on Moscow, and on the 25th of September 1941
they began their assault, the panss advanced and even more Soviet troops were captured
but Stalin was determined to defend Moscow to the last.
On October 8, bad weather halted the German advance and they were still 50 miles from Moscow.
Hitler would now pay the price for sending troops South
rather than advancing on Moscow earlier on in the year.
Speed that gave German blitzkrieg tactics the advantage was now obsolete.
The Soviet winter arrived.
German forces thinking the campaign would be over by summer.
What underprepared tank engines would not start, weapons froze
and soldiers were frostbitten as they didn't have the proper clothing, and on December 5
Germany halted its attack.
Stalin then moved his armies from Siberia to the west, more than 30 divisions made their way
who were all well equipped and trained for fighting in the winter.
By December, more than half a million extra men were in place.
With additional support, the Soviets began a counter attack
driving German forces back for the next seven days Soviet troops tore into German forces.
Hitler ordered for there to be no more retreats
he told his forces they should fight and if necessary, die where they stood
the German line held strong.
For the next four months
the two sides fought and Hitler hadn't got the quick results that he'd wanted or planned, hated.
His army then moved south in search for oil, and began a campaign of securing Stalingrad
and so began one of the longest battles of the Second World War
the city had to be taken streets by street, house by house and room by room.
But the Soviet two began to move troops and equipment southwards
more than a million men 900 tanks and more than 1000 aircraft removed to the battle zone
and attack the German flank.
It was now the Germans who surrendered in the 1000s.
Over 100,000 men made their way to captivity, with only 5000, eventually returning to Germany
Germany lost 300,000 men in the Battle of Stalingrad and the Soviets around the same numbers
but the tide of the battle had begun to turn.
The Soviet Army continued its success.
German troops began to withdraw to protect their flank
and the Soviet winter offensive saw them gain lots of territory.
Over the course of a few months, Germany had lost over a million men.
The Soviet Army mobilized further and drove back the German lines at Kursk
never again with the German war machine launch and offensive in the east.
Across the globe on the 26th of November 1941
a Japanese carrier fleet set sail in the northern Pacific, its target was a US naval base in Hawaii
which went by the name of Pearl Harbor.
What had been confined to remain the European war
was now to be transformed into the deadliest global conflict in human history.