subversion is the term if you look in it in a dictionary or criminal code to that matter,
usually is explained as a part of activity to destroy things like religion, government system,
political or economical system of a country.
And usually it's linked to espionage and such romantic things as blowing up bridges,
sidetracking trains, clock and Dagger activity in Hollywood style
when what I'm going to talk about now has absolutely nothing to do with the cliche of espionage
or KGB activity of collecting information.
So the greatest mistake or Miss Miss misconception, I think,
is that whenever we are talking about KGB for some strange reason,
starting from Hollywood movie makers to professors of political science,
and quote unquote experts on Soviet affairs or kremlinologists as they call themselves,
they think that the most desirable thing for
drop off and the whole KGB is to steal blueprints of some supersonic jet,
bring it back to the Soviet Union and sell it to the Soviet military industrial complex
is only partly true.
If we take the whole time, money
and manpower that the Soviet Union and KGB in particular spends outside of USSR border
will discover Of course,
there are no official statistics unlike with CIA or FBI that the Espionage as such
occupies only 10 to 15% of money, time and manpower 15% of the activity of KGB,
the rest 85% is always subversion.
And unlike a dictionary of English Oxford Dictionary,
subversion in Soviet terminology means all these destructive aggressive activity
a to destroy the country, nation or geographical area of your enemy.
So there is no romantics in there absolutely no blowing up bridges,
no microfilms and Coca Cola cans, nothing of that sort.
No James Bond nonsense.
It's most of the This activity is overt,
legitimate and easily observable if you give yourself time and trouble to observe it.
But according to the law, and law enforcement systems of the Western civilization,
it's not a crime, exactly because of misconception, manipulation of terms
within that subverting is a person who is going to blow up our beautiful bridges.
No.
So verter is a student who come for exchange a diplomat, an actor, an artist, a journalist,
like myself, was 10 years ago.
Now, subversion is an activity, which is a two way traffic.
You cannot subvert an enemy, which doesn't want to be subverted.
If you know history of Japan, for example, default till 20th century Japan was a closed society.
The moment of foreign boats comes to the shores of Japan,
the Imperial Japanese Army politely tell them to get lost.
And the American salesman comes to the shore of Japan, let's say 60 or 70 years from now that
and says oh, I have a very beautiful vacuum cleaner for you know, the good financing.
Please leave us with the need your vacuum cleaner.
If they don't leave, they should come to preserve their culture, ideology, traditions,
values impact.
You were not able to subvert Japan.
You cannot subvert Soviet Union.
Because the borders are closed.
The media is censored by the government.
The population is controlled by the KGB and internal police.
But all the beautiful glossy pictures of Time Magazine,
and there is an American which is published by the American Embassy in Moscow.
You can not subvert Soviet citizens because the magazine never reaches Soviet citizens.
Its collapse From the new stance and thrown to garbage can.
Subversion can be only successful when the initiator they act or the Act,
the agent of subversion has a responsive target.
It's a two way traffic.
United States is a receptive target of subversion.
There is no response similar to that one, from United States to the Soviet Union.
It stops halfway somewhere it never reaches here.
The theory of subversion goes all the way back to 1500 years ago,
the first human being who formulated the tactics of subversion was a Chinese philosopher,
by the name of some to 3500 years BC was an advisor for several Imperial courts in ancient China.
And he said, after a long meditation,
that to implement for him to implement state policy in a warlike manner.
It's the most counterproductive, barbaric and inefficient to fight on a battlefield.
You know that war is continuation of state policy, right?
So if you want successfully to implement your state policy, and you start fighting,
this is the most idiotic way to do the highest art of warfare is not to fight at all.
But to subvert anything of value in the country of your enemy, until such time,
that the perception of reality of your enemy
is screwed up to such an extent that he does not perceive you as an enemy.
And that your system, your civilization and your ambitions, look to your enemy as an alternative,
if not desirable, then at least feasible.
Better read, and then there's the ultimate purpose.
The final stage of subversion,
after which you can simply take your enemy without a single shot being fired.
Subversion successful This is basically what subversion as you see,
not a single mentioning of blowing up bridges, of course, sons,
they did know about blowing up bridges, maybe they were not that many bridges at that time.
But the basics of subversion
is being taught to every student of KGB school in USSR and to officers of military academies.
I'm not sure if the same author is included in the list of reading for American officers,
to say nothing about ordinary students of political science.
I had difficulty to find the translation of sunset in in the library of a university in
Toronto and later on here in Los Angeles.
But it's a it's a book which is not available, it is forced to every students in USA
every student who is who is thought to be dealing further in his future career with foreigners.
What's the version is basically it consists of four periods time wise,
if we start from here and go this way time right this is the beginning point.
The first stage of subversion is the process which is called basically demoralisation
says for itself what it is,
it thinks from say 15 to 20 years to demoralize a society wide by 15 or 20 years.
This is the time sufficient to educate one generation of students or children, one generation,
one lifetime span of a person a human being,
which is dedicated to study to shaping up the outlook ideology, personality, no more no less.
Usually it takes from 15 to 20 years.
Well that includes it includes influencing or by various methods infiltration
propaganda Methods direct contracts doesn't really matter.
I will describe them later of various areas where public opinion is formulated or shaped.
Religion, educational system, social life, administration, law enforcement system, military,
of course, and labor and employer relations, economy, okay,
five areas I will not write them down because we will not have enough space.
Some sometimes when I describe all the methods, students ask me question,
Are you sure this is the result of the Soviet influence?
Not necessarily.
You said that practical subversion, about which I'm talking is similar to the martial art,
the Japanese martial art.
If you're if some of you familiar with that tactic,
probably you will remember that if an enemy is bigger and heavier than yourself,
it will be very painful to resist his direct strike.
If a heavier person wants to strike me in the face,
it would be very naive and counterproductive to stop his blow.
The Chinese and Japanese
Judo art tells us what to do first to avoid the strike than to grab the fist
and continue this movement in the direction where it was before.
Right until the enemy crashes in the wall, you see, so what happens here?
The target country obviously does something wrong.
If it's a free democratic society, there are many different movements within the society.
There obviously in every society, there are people who are against the society,
there may be simple criminals ideological in disagreement with a with a state policy,
conscientious enemies, simply psychotic personalities who are against anything.
But And finally, there are a small group of agents of a foreign nation, but subverted, precoded,
right.
The moment all these movements will be directed in one direction, right?
This is the time to catch the movement and to continue
until the movement forces the whole society into collapse into crisis.
Right.
So that's exactly the martial arts tactic.
We don't stop an enemy, we let him go we help him to go in the direction we want them to go.
And so on the stage of demoralization obviously,
there are tendencies in each society in each country, which are going to
opposite direction from the basic moral values and principles
to take advantage of these movements
to capitalize on them is the main purpose of the originator of subversion.
So we have religion, we have education, we have social life, we have power structure,
we have labor relations, unions and finally we have law and order 123456 Okay,
these are the areas of application of subversion, what it is exactly,
in case of religion destroyed, ridicule it, replace it with various sects, cults,
which bring people's attention, faith, whether it is naive, primitive, doesn't really matter.
As long as the basically accepted religious dogma is being slowly eroded
and taken away from the supreme purpose of religion to keep people
in touch with with the Supreme Being that serves the purpose therefore, replays, accepted,
respected, religious organizations with fake organizations,
distract people attention from the real faith and attract them to various different faith
education.
This dragged them from learning something which is constructive, pragmatic, efficient,
instead of mathematics, physics, foreign languages, chemistry,
teach them history of urban warfare, natural foods, economy, your sexuality,
anything long as it takes you away.
Okay.
Social Life
Replace traditionally established institutions and organizations with fake organizations,
take away the initiative from people take away the responsibility
from naturally established links between
individuals group of individuals and society at large,
and replace them with artificially bureaucratically controlled bodies.
Instead of social life and friendship between neighbors, establish social workers,
institutions, people who are on payroll of whom?
Society No, eurocracy, the main concern of social workers is not your family, not you,
not social relations between groups of people,
the main concern is to get the paycheck from the government.
What will be the result of their social work doesn't really matter.
They can develop all kinds of concepts
to show them to show to the government and to the people that they're useful.
Okay, away from the natural links, power structure, okay.
The natural bodies of administration, which are traditionally either elected by,
by people at large or appointed by elected leaders of society,
are being actively substituted by artificial bodies.
The bodies of people, groups of people who nobody elected, never, as a matter of fact,
most of the people don't like them at all, and yet they exist.
One such group is media, who elected them?
How come?
How come they face?
They have so much power, almost monopolistic power on your mind, they can raise your mind.
But who elected them?
How come?
They are they have a nerve to decide what is good and what is bad for
for the elected by you president and his administration, who they alarming.
Spiro Agnew, who was hated by the liberal left, call them a bunch of enfeebled snobs.
And that's exactly what they are.
They think they know they don't say the level of mediocracy.
In a big establishment like New York Times, Los Angeles Times major television network,
you don't have to be excellent journalist.
You have to be exactly a mediocre journalist that's easier to survive.
There's not competition anymore.
You have your good, nice income $100,000 a year.
That's it, whether you're better or worse, doesn't really matter anymore.
As soon as you're smiling to the camera, and do your job.
That's it no more, no more competition.
Power structure slowly is eroded
by the bodies and groups of people who do not have neither qualification nor the will of people
to keep them in power.
And yet they do have power.
Okay.
Together with that there is another process.
Law enforcement law and order, organization and structure is being eroded.
For the last 2025 years, you you if you see all movies and new movies, you can see that in new movies,
a policeman, an officer of the United States Army looks dumb, angry, psychotic, paranoid,
a criminal looks nice kind of, well, he smokes hash and shoots the whatever drug but basically,
he's a nice human being.
He's creative.
And he's unproductive only because society oppressive,
whereby a general Pentagon is always by definition of a war maniac.
A policeman is a big road policeman, he abuses his power.
Not a generality, generalization, like the hatred,
the mistrust to the people who supposed to protect you,
and enforce law and order moral relativity.
The Angela Warner process last two years in Los Angeles, relativity.
The Angela Warner process lasted two years in Los Angeles.
And yet there are still some lawyers who say look, here's a nice character.
As a matter of fact, there was some witness was said also criminal.
For said, while he was a nice guy, I asked him one day to burn a house of my enemy and he wouldn't do it.
Slow substitution of basic moral principles
whereby a criminal is not a criminal actually is a defendant even if his guilt is proven.
There is to adult, to kill or not to feel to be or not to be die shall not kill Yes.
But this line may not necessarily be applicable to a murder,
they shall not murder that should be the presumption not not that they shall not kill.
Okay, Labor Relations at this stage within 15 to 30 years,
we destroy the traditionally established links of bargaining between employer and employee.
The classical Marxist Leninist theory of natural exchange of goods.
A person A has five sacks of grain and Person B has five pairs of shoes
of natural exchange without money is when they bargain between each other.
And only within production of the third foresee an entirely third foreign stranger who says no,
don't give him five sacks of bringing it to me.
And you give me your five pairs of shoes and I will distribute it accordingly.
So the economy will go.
This is the death of natural exchange that depth of natural bargaining.
Well, trade unions were established 100 years ago,
the objective was to improve working conditions and to protect the rights of workers
from those employers who are abusing their their right because they have more money.
Objective at that time, initially, the trade union movement did work.
What we see now is that the bargaining process is no longer resulting into in the compromise,
which is leading objectively to betterment of working conditions and increase of salary,
what we see is that after each prolonged strike, the workers lose.
Even if they have a 10% increase of their salaries,
they cannot catch up due to inflation and due to miss time, more than that,
millions of people suffer from that strike.
Because economy now is interdependent.
It's intertwined like one body.
If previously, steel workers say 100 years ago could strike and nobody would suffer.
Now it's impossible anymore.
If a garbage collector strikes today, the rest of the multimillion city is stinking.
I mean that there is no more service.
In Quebec For example, we have the electricians who are on strike in the middle of winter.
You can freeze your bottom and base to work on strike.
Did they catch up with the Soviet bloc they lost?
Who benefited the leaders of trade unions?
What is the motivation for strike informing improving of work workers condition?
No, obviously it's not.
Then what is it? I do Logie to prove to these capitalists
and the obedient horde of workers like sheep follow these people and they cannot disobey Why?
Because if they do you know what happens to them tickets,
murders shooting truck drivers by picketers.
In Montreal, for example, I saw with my own eyes when I was correspondent of CBC international
Canadian Broadcasting Corporation.
When the work is of aircraft factory destroyed computers and the equipment in the factory and
the administration employed strikebreakers their cars were turned upside down and burned.
Their houses were burned,
their kids were intimidated and some victims were there of that can be sure why
to improve conditions of workers.
Now, ideology okay.
So, this is what happens basically, it may or may not happen without the help of the Soviet Union.
But the natural tendencies
are being greatly taken advantage of and capitalized by the Soviet propaganda systems how
whenever trade union strikes,
we have influx of propaganda mass media ideological dissemination to workers,
right and repeated like parrots, yes workers, right, whose rights workers know the only
freedom of workers to sell his labor according to his own design will
is taken away from him by whom, by trade union boss, unlimited power is given responsibility.
I want to sell my labor not for 250 an hour but for $2 I didn't have rights.
My freedom is denied to me. I know that if I sell my work for two for $2 an hour Not for $3 now,
I will compete better with it with the other guy who is lazy and more greedy.
I don't need to $3 I need only $2 No, I was made to believe by media,
by business by advertising agencies that I need more and more and more.
Have you ever heard any advertising on TV to consume less?
No, no wait.
Whether you need a six cylinder car or not, you have to buy it and hurry up.
When I was driving here on the local radio station unexcited announcer said, You hurry up,
rush and save, save save there is a plenty hoses sale?
Save by buying more?
Of course, of course, it would be too naive to expect the KGB mags that advertising agency
to do such a crazy commercial?
No, of course not.
But what we did when I was working for policy press, we would snow plow editorial offices,
student organizations, religious group with literature of class struggle,
may if not directly Marxist Leninist propaganda,
then a propaganda of over legitimate aspirations of working class, betterment of life equality,
equality mindview.
President Kennedy once said, people we will make America to believe that people are born equal,
are people born equal?
Is there any mentioning in the Bible or any other Holy Scripture in any religion, any religion,
if you don't believe me, go to library and check it.
There is not a single word about equality.
Just the opposite.
By your deeds, God will judge you.
What you do is important, the merit of your personality.
You cannot legislate the quality.
If you want to be equal, you have to be equal, you have to deserve it.
And yet we've built our society.
On the principle of equality, we say people are equal, we know it is false.
It's a lie.
Some people are tall and stupid.
Others are short, bold and clever.
If we make them if we make them equal by force, if we put the principle of equality,
in the basis of our social political structure, is the same thing as building a house on sand.
Sooner or later, it will collapse.
And that's exactly what happens.
And we as Soviet propaganda makers are trying to
push you in the direction which you go yourself equality, yes,
equality people are equal land of equal opportunities.
Is it true or not?
Think about equal opportunities, should they be equal opportunity for me,
and for a lazy bastard who come here
from some other country and immediately registers as a welfare recipient benefits.
I never received a single note Sorry, I did this once.
But I never applied for welfare for the 13 years, I took any job, security guard, journalist,
taxi driver, anything.
While I was restless, but some people don't like it.
They immediate so why should we be Why should we have equal opportunities?
Why the Equal Opportunity to excel?
Equal Opportunity in equal circumstances?
Yes, but you know, people are different to excel.
Yes.
Provided we reach the same level of excellence See, perfection,
which is hypothetical distant future.
Yes, maybe.
But we know perfectly well that even with the best intentions, people could not be equal.
Why should we have equality in the same legal system, myself?
I'm considering myself a law abiding citizen.
And the person who comes here
to rob and shoot safe the United States administration on the card important
1000s of Cuban criminals.
They were non criminals.
Yet they were accepted.
Do you think it's fair if myself and my wife from Philippines who worked Like, excuse me, Horace,
as a lab technician in the hospital should have the same rights as a criminal film from Cuba.
And yet very Peters parents equality, equality, equality.
And
the solid propaganda system helps us to believe that equality is something which is desirable.
Democracy as it was established by fathers of this country of the system, and the last century, is,
is not equality is the system where different people
and equal people have a chance to survive and help each other in constant competition
in constant perfection, not inequality,
which is super imposed from from godfather or nice person in Washington, DC.
And the absolute equality exists in Soviet Union, quote unquote, equality.
Everybody is equally injured.
Except some people are more equal than the others in Politburo.
So the moment you you bring a country
to the point of almost total demoralization when nothing works anymore,
when you are not sure that there's right or wrong, good and bad.
But there's no division between evil and good.
When even the leaders of church sometimes say, well, violence for the sake of justice,
especially social justice is justified in the countries like Nicaragua, El Salvador, well,
maybe Rhodesia.
And we listen to them and say, Yeah, probably.
It's true.
Is it true?
No, it is not true.
Violence is not justified, especially for the sake of quote unquote,
social justice introduced by Marxist Leninist,
that this might form a call from novice Defense Agency.
Okay, so where is the point?
The next step?
Is this the realization?
Again, this word says for itself, what it is to destabilize all the relations,
all the accepted institutions, and organizations in a country of your enemy, how you do it.
You don't have to send up a battalion of KGB agents to blow up bridges.
No, you let them do it themselves.
The area of application is again, it's it's narrower now, not like the previous case.
The overt legitimate actions of the of the KGB in this case, would be hardly noticeable.
There is no crime
if a professor who recently went to USSR introduces a course of Marxism leninism.
In California, in college, for example, nobody is going to come to his doorstep and say, Okay, Mr.
Come, you're under arrest.
No, it's not a crime.
It's not even considered a moral crime against your country.
So the area of application here is narrowing down to economy.
Again, labor relations right.
To law and order.
Plus military and the economy is law and order.
Yes.
Again, the media but wider scope a little bit different.
I'll explain when Okay, basically precarious economy,
the radicalization of bargaining process, if on that stage,
we still could achieve theoretically some positive compromise between the
negotiating sides with with say, the arbitrary introduction of arbitrary judges,
third side objective the judging the demands of both sides, here it's radicalization.
On this on the stage of this civilization, we cannot come to compromise even within a family,
the husband and wife couldn't figure out which is better.
Husband wants his kids to eat at the table and wife wants him child to roam around the room and,
and drop food all over the floor.
They cannot come to compromise unless they start a fight.
It's impossible to reach a compromise constructive compromise between neighbors.
Some people say I don't like you to watering
your lawn at that time because exactly at the time I'm walking my dog and he's getting nervous.
He cannot pass his balls, you know,
they cannot compromise they go to a civil court or something like that.
Radicalization of human relations.
Normal compromise, fight fight fight.
The normal traditionally accepted relations are destabilized
the relations between teachers and students in schools and colleges fight
the relations between in economical sphere between labors and employers are further
radicalized.
No more acceptance of the legitimacy of demands of workers.
Unlike Japanese, with the theory z if you ever heard about it,
where the workers are involved in decision making process therefore they don't have
moral incentive to fight their their bosses in the United States is just the opposite.
The harder is the fight the better the more heroic they look,
when the Greyhound network was on strike recently, the correspondence of local TV networks
all over the United States were approaching the strikers and they say oh, yes,
we are doing something nice.
They look like heroes and they were proud, there was some family the husband was a bus driver.
Now they decided in in the protest against the bosses to camp somewhere in the forest.
And they were presented to the to the audience as as a heroic nice people.
You see, the violent clashes between passengers picketers and the strikers
are presented as something normal 10 1520 years ago, we would we would be would be angry.
So why why why so much hatred.
Today we are not received well.
Commonplace, read radicalization.
Militarisation sometimes, as I explained, on that stage,
I took a step a little bit further shooting people, okay, Law and Order now also is
pushed into the area where previously people settled their differences
peacefully and legitimately.
Now, we are getting rid this court cases in the in this smallest irrelevant cases,
we cannot solve our problems anymore.
The society at large becomes more and more antagonistic.
Between individuals within groups of individuals and the society at large.
The media puts himself in the opposition to the society in general at large, separate, alienated.
Okay.
On that stage, you remember, I was talking a couple of hours ago about the sleepers.
That's when the students from say United States, if they are training in the warmer University,
or developing nations,
that's the students I was dealing with are being sent back from the Soviet Union here,
or if they were already in the united states in the country, which is an object of subversion.
They spring to action, the sleepers go up.
They slept for 15 to 20 years.
Now they become leaders of groups, preachers.
I don't know, public public figures prominently they act they actively
include themselves in the political process.
All of a sudden we see a homosexual 15 years ago, he did his dirty job and nobody cared.
Now he makes it a political issue, a political issue.
He demands recognition, respect human rights,
and Iran is a large group of people and their violent clashes between him and police,
his group and ordinary people, no matter what it's black against white,
yellow is again green doesn't matter where his division line goes.
As long as this group come into antagonistic clash, sometimes militant, Li,
sometimes we fire arms.
That is this civilization process.
The sleepers, many of whom are simply KGB agents, become leaders
of the process of this civilization
doesn't mean the cameras on top of suns camera divano of the United States.
The person who takes care is already here is a respected citizen of the United States.
Sometimes he gets money from various foundations for for his legitimate
struggle for I don't know human rights women rights kid live, presumably whatever.
There are sympathetic Americans who donate their money to this the good life.
This sterilization process usually leads directly to the process of crisis.
In case of developing nations, there's the area where I was active, the process starts when,
when the legitimate bodies of power, the social structure collapses,
it cannot function anymore.
So, instead, we have artificials body injected into society such as non elected committees.
Remember, I was talking about them here, social workers, who are not elected by people media,
who self who are self appointed rulers of your opinion, some strange groups,
which claim that they know how to lead society forward,
they don't usually only cares how to collect the nations and,
and promote and sell their own concocted ideology, mixture of religion and ideology.
Here, we have all this artificials body claiming power.
If the power is denied to them, they take it by force.
In case of Iran, for example, all of a sudden, we have revolutionary committees,
who what what kind of revolution there was no revolution yet, and yet they had the committees.
They were taking power of judgment they have, they have the power of execution,
they had the power of legislation, and that they had the power of judicial,
all of them combined in one person who is half baked intellectual,
sometimes graduated from Harvard University or Berkeley.
He comes back to his country and
he thinks that he knows the answer to all the social economical problems.
Okay, crisis is when society cannot function any more productively it collapses, obviously,
that's the word for crisis.
So therefore, the population at large is looking for a savior.
The religious groups are expecting the Messiah to come.
The workers say we have family to feed.
Let's have a strong government, maybe socialist government centralized when when somebody put
put the employers on their place and
let us work we are sick and tired of going to strike and missing overtime and all that stuff.
We need some strong men strong government, a leader a Savior is needed.
Population is sick and tired already.
And here we are, we have a savior, either a foreign nation comes in,
or the local group of leftist Marxist no matter what they call themselves Sandinista
Reverend or some sort.
Bishop mozarella, like in Zimbabwe, doesn't matter.
A savior comes and says I will lead you.
So we have two alternatives here.
Civil War and invasion.
See how it goes.
Civil War we know what it is Lebanon is the is the best example.
The Civil War, which was artificially implanted in Lebanon by injection of force of PLO,
Palestinian Liberation Organization
invasion we have in many other countries like Afghanistan.
And then any East European country, it was invaded by the Soviet Army.
But the result is the same The next stage is normalization.
Normalization is a very ironic word of course.
It is borrowed from 1968 situation in Czechoslovakia when the Soviet propaganda
and after them New York Times declared the country is normalized, the tanks moved into Prague,
so there is no more Prague Spring, there is no more violence, normal normalization.
At that stage, the self appointed rulers of the society don't need any revolution anymore.
They don't need any radicalism anymore.
So this is the reverse from this civilization.
Basically, it is stabilizing the country by force.
So all this sleepers and activists and social workers and liberals
and homosexuals and professors and Marxist Leninist are being eliminated.
Physically, sometimes you They've done their job already.
Okay, they're not needed anymore.
The new rulers need stability to exploit the nation to exploit the country to take advantages
of the victory.
Okay, so no more evolution is plays.
And that's exactly what happens in number of countries.
You remember Bangladesh, this is the crisis in which I was instrumental.
First they had Mujibur Rahman.
In 1971, he was the leader of People's Party awami League.
With mustache like Stalin.
He was in Russia many times.
In five years, he was shot by his former colleagues, Marxists.
He fulfilled his function in Afghanistan, it happened three times.
Because there was turkey then there was a mean now there's Barbara karma,
they killed each other successively.
One after another, the moment he fulfills his duty, the first one demoralized country,
the second destabilize, the third one brought it to crisis.
Goodbye, Congress.
Barbara Carmel comes from Moscow and put them into the seat of power.
Same thing happened in Grenada recently.
Maurice Bishop, Marxist was killed by Austin,
what's his name general something was also a Marxist.
Right?
So no more revolutions please.
Normalization now, from now on.
Normal strikes normal homosexual sexuals.
Normal women lead normal kidlit normally period.
Good, solid, democratic proletarian freedom.
To reverse this process, takes enormous effort went today,
United States had to invade Grenada to reverse the process of subversion.
Some people say boy, this is not good.
It's not kosher, to invade the beautiful country island of Grenada.
Well, why didn't you stop the process here?
When Grenada was just approached by leftists?
Why not to prevent Maurice bishop to come in power in the first place did Grenadines want him
very questionable.
They didn't know who was more inspiration from the first place.
He came to power by coup d'etat himself.
Okay, now we let the situation develop further and further and further until the crisis
and normalization very soon.
And then United States decided to invade country discovering that
the country was absolutely a military base for the Soviet Union.
Of course, it's a drastic measure.
Of course, it's a pity that Marine Corps had to lose what 17 lines very bad,
why not to stop the process before it comes to prices,
or no intellectuals will not let you it's interference into into domestic affairs.
They're very careful not to not not to let American administration to interfere
in domestic affairs of Latin American caucus.
They don't mind Soviet Union interfere in this affair.
So to reverse this process, from here, it takes only and always military force,
no other force on earth can reverse this process at this point.
At this point, it does not take military invasion of the United States.
It takes strong action like in Chile as CIA covert involvement,
to prevent the Savior from outside to come into power
and to stabilize country before it erupts into civil war
country before it erupts into civil war.
Support the right wing conservative forces by money by crook so love doesn't matter
sterilized and don't let the crisis develop into into civil war or invasion
or no your liberals will say it's against the law.
The Congress will not appropriate money for covert actions.
So CIA Why not?
Should we wait till the normalization come in?
So good thanks landed in Los Angeles airport.
Now, at that point, at the point of this civilization also the process could be reversed
again easily then this no CIA involvement at this point.
You know, what it takes here?
Restriction of some liberties for small groups, which are self declared enemies of the society.
As simple as that all know,
the median liberals will tell you this is against the American Constitution.
How can we by force denied the civil rights to criminals for example, it's not good.
Okay.
So we allow them to okay.
If you Allow the criminals to have civil rights go on bring the country to the crisis.
This is a bloodless way to do curb the rights and not to put them in prison.
No, no, I'm not talking about putting all the gays from San Francisco in the concentration camp,
do not allow them to take political force, do not elect them to the seats of power,
whether it is municipality level, state level or federal level.
It has to be bitten in the hands of American voters,
at a person like that in the city of power is an enemy.
Do not be afraid of this word, it is an end.
If he is not an enemy here, he will be here.
Later on, he will be short of course.
But at this point, he is a man.
Okay, you're doing great service by denying him a right
to capitalize on his own crazy ideas and become a powerful man, a man who uses the seat of power.
Restriction of certain freedoms and permissiveness at that point, would prevent
sliding into crisis and probably will return the process of this civilization
to curb unlimited power,
monopolistic power of trade unions here at that point would say economy from collapsing,
to introduce a law to stop private companies of raping public opinions mine
in in the in the direction of consumerism,
no company must have a right to force you into buying more unless you want it must be a law.
You want to advertise your your car, okay.
But not a single mentioning of buying it now and saving money.
It must be against the law to force people to consume more self restrain.
Previously, before this process started, the self restrain was the business of church religion.
Because our preachers, the fathers of church will tell us material values are good,
but it's not the prime function of human being.
Because you have to leave them something.
Obviously the design for our life is not to consume more the audience is something greater.
It's such a complicated instrument the human body was created.
Obviously, there must be some higher purpose for that.
And it's very easy to avoid this civilization by denying
the greedy companies one little freedom, one little Liberty forcing you
into turning yourself into processors of unwanted products and goods.
They turn you into machines like the warm who does inlet and outlet so
how long an average blinds lots of these days, less than a year?
Why?
Whereas workmanship we want you to buy?
Okay, this liberalization process could be easily overcome if as I say, the society,
by its own will or after persuasion by the leaders will come to the idea of self restrain.
It's so hard we want to consume more but you have to unless you will come to this stage.
When as we say in Russia, if Sahara Desert ever becomes a communist state,
there'll be shortage of sand.
You have to curve your
you have to you have to curve your expectations at this point before it's too late.
But no, we don't want to do it.
Demineralization process.
Again, it's the easiest thing to reverse.
First of all, by restricting import of propaganda, the easiest thing to do and limited,
unrestrained import of Soviet literature.
So the journalists
giving Soviet propaganda and ideological educators equal time on American TV networks.
It has to be stopped.
And it's easy.
They won't they won't be offended minded.
As a matter of fact, they will respect American war.
But then my former colleague Legendre Posner appears on nightline and said, quote, The Last Well,
what do you what do you think about this?
And what can he think?
He is an instrument of propaganda.
He thinks what what comrade Andropov tells us is just a nice articulate mouthpiece of the Soviet
subversion system.
And Ted Koppel makes you believe that my friend Vladimir Posner thinks,
the process of demoralization may not have started at all, if at that point, the country,
which is a recipient of subversion, actively, not violently,
but actively prevents importation of foreign ideology.
I don't want America to follow the pattern of ancient Japan,
you don't have to shoot every foreigner when it approaches
the sacred borders of the United States.
But when he offers you a junk in the disguise of very shiny, something, you have to tell him, No,
we have our own junk.
If at that point, the society is strong, brave,
and conscientious enough to stop importation of ideas which are foreign,
then the whole chain of events could be prevented.
Recently, I've been to Philippines, and I was shocked.
How in big cities like Manila, children listened to deafening music,
and melodious nation with long traditions of good, nice ethnic music.
Introduced by Spanish long time ago, maybe two centuries, three centuries ago,
I don't remember all of a sudden listen to musical garbage
blasting their radios at full blast of the full volume.
Why?
In India, I spent many years watching the reactions of Indians walking out of movie theaters,
after seeing Hollywood production.
They couldn't figure out why Americans are so wasteful, they smash their cars,
they shiny cars every five minutes.
How can they shoot each other for half million dollars?
Is the truth there?
So sex, sex?
I mean obsessed with sex?
Can you imagine showing a movie where each five minutes there is copulation on the screen?
So a country like India with long traditions, traditional of respect to this private matters?
For to Pakistan?
And United States expect these people to respect you?
No way?
Oh, yes, they will see the movie, they will pay five rupees to see that garbage.
But they walk out and will tell their kids don't respect Americans don't be like Americans.
See?
So.
The process of demoralization could be stopped right here, both as an expert and as an input.
And that takes one step.
One very important thing to do.
You don't have to expel all the KGB agents from Washington DC.
The most difficult and at the same time, the simplest answer to the subversion is to start here,
and even before by bringing back the society to religion,
something that you cannot touch and eat and put on yourself.
But something that rules society and makes it move and preserve it.
The Soviet scientists,
suffering which has nothing to do with religion is a computer scientists.
The very intensive research on the history of socialist countries.
He calls socialist or communist,
any country with a centralized economy and the pyramid will spiral of power structure.
And he discovered Actually, he didn't discover it he just brought to the attention of his readers
that civilizations like Maharaja Daro in the Premier Hindus area, like Egypt, like Maya Incas,
like below, but the lorgnette culture collapse and disappeared from the surface of
the moment they lost religion.
As simple as that they disintegrated.
Nobody remembers them anymore.
Well, distantly.
So the ideas are moving society and keeping mankind as a society of human beings intelligent,
moral agents of God.
The facts, the truth, the exact knowledge may not
all the sophisticated technology and computers will not prevent society from disintegrating,
and eventually dying out.
Have you ever met a person who would sacrifice his life freedom for the truth like that?
This is truth.
I never met the person who said this is truth, and I'm ready to shoot me the truth.
But millions sacrificed their life, freedom, comfort,
everything for things like God like Jesus Christ,
it's an on some martyrs in the Soviet concentration camp died.
And they died in peace.
Unlike those who shouted long leave Stalin, knowing perfectly well that you may not live long.
Something which is something which is not material, moves society and helps it to survive.
And the other way around,
the moment we turn into two by two is four and make it the guiding principle of our life,
our existence, we die, even though this is true,
and this we cannot prove when we can feel and have faith.
So the answer to ideological subversion, strangely enough is very simple.
You don't have to shoot people.
You don't have
to aim missiles and Pershing's and cruise missiles at unbreakable headquarters.
You simply have to have faith and prevent suppression.
In other words, not to be a victim of subversion.
Don't try to be a person who in judo is trying to smash your enemy and being caught by your hand.
Don't strike like that.
Strike with power your spirit and moral superiority.
If you don't have the power, it's high time to develop it.
And that's the only answer